<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Rubber on Rahardhika | Comparative Historical Sociology in Southeast Asia</title><link>https://www.rahardhika.com/tags/rubber/</link><description>Recent content in Rubber on Rahardhika | Comparative Historical Sociology in Southeast Asia</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2020 a hugo theme by [somrat](https://github.com/Somrat37/somrat); All images &amp;copy; 2013-2020 Rahardhika Utama.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.rahardhika.com/tags/rubber/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why does land reform thrive in some countries but fail in others?</title><link>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/why_land_reform_fails/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/why_land_reform_fails/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;To answer this question, we need to step back and ask, “Why do we need land reform in the first place to solve the global poverty problem?” Land reform can improve agricultural productivity and rural livelihoods. Since the majority of the global poor population lives in rural areas and depends on the agricultural sector for their livelihood, land reform can potentially help alleviate global poverty. According to a recent &lt;a href="https://www.worldbank.org/en/topic/agriculture/overview"&gt;World Bank report&lt;/a&gt;, agricultural development is one of the most powerful tools to end extreme poverty and boost shared prosperity. Implementing land reform can lead to growth in the agricultural sector, which has been demonstrated to be &lt;a href="https://documents.worldbank.org/en/publication/documents-reports/documentdetail/700061468334490682/ending-poverty-and-hunger-by-2030-an-agenda-for-the-global-food-system"&gt;two to four times more effective in increasing the income of the poorest&lt;/a&gt; compared to other sectors.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Social Life of Rubber</title><link>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/social_life_rubber/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/social_life_rubber/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Natural rubber remains an important global commodity despite the increasing consumption of its synthetic counterpart. Rubber is native to the Amazonian rainforest, it was smuggled to Britain in 1876 and massively cultivated in Southeast Asian plantations from then to now. The circulation of rubber has produced diverse forms of social relations throughout the history of modern civilization. How does the life story of rubber help us understand global inequality? Find out in this video.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The old man and his old trees</title><link>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/old_man_old_trees/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/old_man_old_trees/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sutopo is a seventy-eight-year-old rubber farmer of Sumatra who owns a small plot of old rubber trees &lt;em&gt;(Hevea braziliansis)&lt;/em&gt;. He planted most of his trees forty years ago from low-quality rubber seeds he gleaned from nearby state-owned rubber plantations.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.rahardhika.com/images/blog/rubber2.jpg" alt="Rubber Farmer"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;© 2017 Rahardhika Utama&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, the rubber tree is no longer productive for latex taping after twenty years, and trees that are germinated from rubber seeds produce lower yields of latex. Today, rubber farmers in North Sumatra are usually elderly persons as young people prefer working in the cities and leaving their parents struggling with their family land in the villages. The combination of elderly farmers and old rubber trees makes up for low productivity of the overall smallholder rubber sector in this area.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>