<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Photography on Rahardhika | Comparative Historical Sociology in Southeast Asia</title><link>https://www.rahardhika.com/tags/photography/</link><description>Recent content in Photography on Rahardhika | Comparative Historical Sociology in Southeast Asia</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2020 a hugo theme by [somrat](https://github.com/Somrat37/somrat); All images &amp;copy; 2013-2020 Rahardhika Utama.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.rahardhika.com/tags/photography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The old man and his old trees</title><link>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/old_man_old_trees/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/old_man_old_trees/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sutopo is a seventy-eight-year-old rubber farmer of Sumatra who owns a small plot of old rubber trees &lt;em&gt;(Hevea braziliansis)&lt;/em&gt;. He planted most of his trees forty years ago from low-quality rubber seeds he gleaned from nearby state-owned rubber plantations.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.rahardhika.com/images/blog/rubber2.jpg" alt="Rubber Farmer"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;© 2017 Rahardhika Utama&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, the rubber tree is no longer productive for latex taping after twenty years, and trees that are germinated from rubber seeds produce lower yields of latex. Today, rubber farmers in North Sumatra are usually elderly persons as young people prefer working in the cities and leaving their parents struggling with their family land in the villages. The combination of elderly farmers and old rubber trees makes up for low productivity of the overall smallholder rubber sector in this area.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Gunny sack and the precarious workers behind the circular economy</title><link>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/gunny_sacks/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/gunny_sacks/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Yu Djilah, a mother of three, could no longer find a job as a seasonal farmworker since the expansion of the male-dominated sugar cane plantations to her village. She used to work for food-crop farmers cultivating rice, corn, and soybean. In the past decade, Indonesia saw an increasing trend of importing these commodities and thus threatening the local commodity market, which further compelled affluent landowners to convert their farms into sugar cane plantations in her village.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Saving the Inguls</title><link>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/saving_inguls/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/saving_inguls/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The “Ingul” tree &lt;em&gt;(Toona sureni)&lt;/em&gt; has been disappearing from Samosir Island, Indonesia. This tree holds an essential role in sustaining the traditional culture in the island through its utility as the wood for building fishmonger canoes and traditional houses.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.rahardhika.com/images/blog/ingul2.jpg" alt="Saving the Inguls"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;© 2017 Rahardhika Utama&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mama Ina committed to planting the Ingul trees in the forest area that surrounds her village for almost two years. She hopes to preserve the traditional culture by making sure there will be sufficient supply of Ingul woods in the island for future generations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Tobanese fishmongers entrapped in the net of big fishery companies</title><link>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/lake_toba_fishmonger/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.rahardhika.com/blog/lake_toba_fishmonger/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Fishmongers in Lake Toba, Indonesia, the largest volcanic lake in the world, are living witnesses for the degrading water quality in the lake due to the waste of floating net cage fishery companies in recent years.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.rahardhika.com/images/blog/laketoba2.jpg" alt="Fishmongers cleaning nets on Lake Toba"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;© 2017 Rahardhika Utama&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took the first two photos while I asked them if they would have the slightest chance of pursuing the local government to deal with the water pollution problem; they laughed at my question.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>